Guide to the Jay McInerney papers, 1971-1989
McInerney, Jay papers, 1971-1989
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Jay McInerney papers, 1971-1989
4666
Jay McInerney
1.7 cubic ft.
Personal correspondence, professional and publishing correspondence, photographs, videocassettes and audiocassettes, fan mail, two scrapbooks, ephemeral items, and newsclippings.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The Jay McInerney papers consist of personal correspondence, professional and publishing correspondence, photographs, and other papers relating chiefly to the publicity for his novel Bright Lights Big City.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Jay McInerney is the author of Bright Lights Big City, Ransom, and other novels.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The Jay McInerney papers consist of personal correspondence, professional and publishing correspondence, photographs, and other papers relating chiefly to the publicity for his novel Bright Lights Big City. The collection includes manuscripts of McInerney's other published and unpublished writing, and drafts and screenplay drafts of Bright Lights Big City. The collection also includes videocassettes and audiocassettes, fan mail, two scrapbooks (dissembled) that chronicle the personal life and professional and literary presence of Jay McInerney and Merry McInerney, ephemeral items, photographs, and newsclippings.
Personal papers include letters and notes from McInerney to his wife Merry; photographs of them and their wedding; material regarding travel, particularly in Africa; incidental diary fragments; and financial and business records. Correspondents include Raymond Carver and Tess Gallagher, McInerney's editor and friend Gary Fisketjon of Random House, and authors Richard Ford, Rust Hills, Paul Bowles, Julian Barnes, Tama Janowitz, Lorrie Moore, Tina Brown, Bill Buford, Gordon Lish, Tobias Wolff, and Mona Simpson.
SUBJECTS
Names:
McInerney, Jay; Carver, Raymond L.; Gallagher, Tess; Lish, Gordon; Moore, Lorrie; Simpson, Mona; Wolff, Tobias, 1945-; Bowles, Paul, 1910-; Brown, Tina; Buford, Bill; Barnes, Julian; Ford, Richard, 1944-; Janowitz, Tama; Hills, L. Rust; McInerney-Whiteford, Merry; Fisketjon, Gary
Subjects:
Novelists, American; Fiction--Stories, plots, etc.; Publicity; Publishers and publishing; Authors, American
Form and Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks; Photographs
Occupations:
Authors
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Personal correspondence
Box 1
Series II. Professional and publishing correspondence
Box 2
Series III. Manuscripts
Box 3
Series IV. Writings
Box 4
Series V. Scrapbooks
Boxes 5-6
Series V. Ephemera
Boxes 7
Series VI. Videocassettes
See Container List
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Personal correspondence
  - Correspondence from Raymond Carver to Jay McInerney, 1971-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letter: February 10, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letter: December 17, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letter: July 23, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letter: January 13, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letter: July 7, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letter: July 15, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Postcard: July 19, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letter: July, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letter: March 28, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Postcard: May 24, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Postcard: June 21, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letter: July 7, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photocopies of correspondence from Carver to McInerney--Letters only, 1971-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence from Tess Gallagher to McInerney, 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letter: June 4, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letter: October 20, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Postcard: January 13, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letter: August 11, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Postcard: 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letter: 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letter: January 21, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letter: March 24, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Poem: 1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence from McInerney to Merry (Reymond) McInerney, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence from McInerney to Merry McInerney, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence from Gary L. Fisketjon to McInerney, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Note with photograph of wine bottles and annotation from Julian Barnes to McInerney, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letter from Tina Brown to McInerney, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letter from Tina Brown to McInerney, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters from Bill Buford to McInerney, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence from Richard Ford to McInerney including one letter from McInerney to Ford never sent, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letter from Rust Hills to McInerney, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letter from Tama Janowitz to McInerney, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters from Gordon Lish to McInerney, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters from Lorrie Moore to McInerney, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters from Mona Simpson to McInerney, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letters from Tobias Wolff to McInerney, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Postcards from McInerney never sent, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Series II. Professional and publishing correspondence
  - Professional and publishing correspondence, 1980-1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Professional and publishing correspondence, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Professional and publishing correspondence, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Professional and publishing correspondence, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Professional and publishing correspondence, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Professional and publishing correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Professional and publishing correspondence, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Notebook with notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous material regarding trip to Africa with Sobek's International Explorers Society, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Notes, 1985; "Notes: Paul Bowles 1985, Tangier (for Vanity Fair piece)" (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Good Help by Allan Gurganus with dedication from author to McInerney, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Paolo Barozzi miscellany, 1981-1986; Note from McInerney, Peggy Guggenheim: Una donna, una collezione, Venezia by Barozzi with personal dedication from author to McInerney, "Peggy Guggenheim Remembered" by Barozzi (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Draft of the play After Hours by Joseph Minion with note from McInerney, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous, 1985-1988; Newspaper article, complimentary drink passes, slide, tour information (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1986-1989; Business cards, addresses and phone numbers, newspaper clippings, notes, American Express credit card (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Series III. Manuscripts
  - Notes, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Revised second draft of Bright Lights, Big City with Michael Ulick's notes, n.d (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Draft of screenplay of Bright Lights--Version 1, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Draft of screenplay of Bright Lights--Version 2, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Draft of screenplay of Bright Lights--Version 3, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Draft of screenplay of Bright Lights--Version 4, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Additional copy of Version 4, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Early draft of Paint It Black, unpublished screenplay, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Early draft of Paint It Black, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - First draft and early notes of Paint It Black, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Manuscript of I-Land Manhattan in Monologue by Sonia Pilcer, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series IV. Writings
  - "The Real Tad Allagash", 1884; First draft--originally entitled "Allagash on the Hudson," rejection letter from Mademoiselle (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "The Real Tad Allagash", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Chapters from an unpublished novel, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "Sympathy", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "Sympathy", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Criticism on "The Nuclear Age" by Tim O'Brien, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Pages 8-11 of unknown story, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Instant Tinsel", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "Where They Be Smoke", n.d.; First and second drafts (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Smoke", 1986-1987; Letters of rejection and acceptance, two drafts of "Smoke," The Atlantic Report author profile, photocopy of article revisions (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - "Bowles Galleys", 1985; Letter from Vanity Fair, photocopy of article revisions (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "Deadly Hazards, Minor Hassles", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "A Sentimental Education", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - "Reunion", 1987; Two drafts, photocopies of article revisions from Esquire (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - "Fear of Dancing", n.d.; Two copies, original article in Esquire (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Introduction to Manhattan Transfer, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Speeches, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Interview, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Series V. Scrapbooks
  - Miscellaneous, 1982-1984; Letters of congratulation, miscellaneous publishing letters, letters regarding "Amanda" and "IT'S 6 AM, DO YOU KNOW WHERE YOU ARE" (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1984; Newspaper clippings, publicity photo, book jacket, miscellaneous publishing letters (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1984-1985; Newspaper clippings, photo of bookstore, miscellaneous letters (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Photocopies and original newspaper clippings, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Photocopies of newspaper clippings, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Fan mail, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Fan mail, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Fan mail, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Fan mail, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Letters received, clippings, Syracuse University administrative papers, 1979-1986 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Negatives and photographs, wedding photographs, publicity photographs, a letter, 1983-1986 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Letters, invitation list, McInerney resume, c. 1985 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Proposal from Playboy, publicity, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Publicity, c. 1985 (Box 6, Folder 5-8)
- Series VI. Ephemera, Sunglasses worn by Michael J. Fox, Bright Lights, Big City t-shirt, photos of McInerney and Merry, flyers, book jackets, newspaper and magazine clippings; audiocassettes: German feature on McInerney and Bret Easton Ellis, and "Why I am Not Moving to Hollywood" by McInerney; McInerney interviews with Paul Bowles (Box 7)
- Series VII. Videocassettes
  - "I Minimalisti", V-343
  - "Bright Lights Big City," Jay McInerney Interviews 4/22/88, V-343